Partial Register of the Boris N. Volkov Papers, 1915-1963
Hoover Institution Archives
Boris N. Volkov Papers
1915-1963
36008
Hoover Institution Archives
1 manuscript box, 23 microfilm reels, digital files (3.9 linear feet)
Speeches and writings, correspondence, clippings, other printed matter, and photographs, relating to Russian literature, the Russian Civil War in Siberia and Mongolia, the career of the White Russian commander Baron Ungern-Shternberg, Russian émigré affairs, and anti-communist movements in the United States. Includes a translation by Elena Varneck and a fictionalized autobiographical account of the Russian Civil War.
Volkov, Boris N., 1894-1954
Access
Collection open for research. The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1936.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biography
B. N. Volkov was born in Ekaterinoslavl' (Siberia) on 30 May 1894 (N.S.). A university student in law, he volunteered for military duty at the front in 1915, serving in Poland and the Caucasus as commander of a medical unit responsible for retrieving wounded soldiers from the front lines. In December 1917, he was involved in an anti-Bolshevik uprising in Irkutsk. During the Russian Civil War, Volkov served as an agent of the Siberian Provisional (later All-Russian) government in Mongolia.
Escaping from Baron R. F. Ungern-Shternberg, who had sentenced him to death, he spent the following few years in China, as a commercial and sales agent for Gilchrist and Co. and the Tientsin Chemical Works Association.
In 1923 Volkov and his wife moved to the United States, where he worked as a longshoreman and construction worker, and at a variety of other jobs. He was also a poet and writer, and though his autobiographical novel, "Conscript to Paradise," was never published, he did see to press a book of verse entitled V pyli chuzhikh dorog (Berlin, 1933). Volkov also wrote for the émigré press, and much of his poetry was published in periodicals. He died in San Francisco on 9 June 1954.
Chronology
1894 May 30 [N.S.] Born, Ekaterinoslav, Russia
1915 Medic, Russian army
1917 Completed university course, Legal Faculty, Moscow University
1918-1920 Agent of Provisional Siberian and All-Russian governments (Omsk) in Mongolia
1923 Emigrated to United States
1933 Author, V pyli chuzhikh dorog
1945 Translator, United Nations
1954 June 9 Died, San Francisco
Scope and Content
This collection consists mainly of the writings of the émigré poet and writer Boris Volkov. During the First World War, Volkov was a medic with the Russian army on its Western and Caucasian fronts. During the Civil War, he was active in the counterrevolutionary uprising in Irkutsk in 1918, and thereafter was an agent of the Omsk government in Mongolia, where he reported on the political and military situation, particularly with regard to the activities of Ataman G. M. Semenov and General Baron R. F. Ungern-Shternberg.
Among his writings, the most significant piece is the unpublished novel "Conscript to Paradise." The novel itself is based in part on his own experiences and in part on the diary of his wife, nee Elena Petrovna Witte, the daughter of the Russian Councilor to the Mongolian government, but the completed draft is significantly abridged from the original version. The original draft is in the form of a large volume of fragments, which may include typescript fragments of Witte's diary (or Volkov's reworked versions of it). The fragments indicate that the author had in mind a much larger autobiographical novel that would have encompassed his adventures in Siberia, the Transbaikal region of the Far East, and Mongolia during the 1917-1921 period. This material has been left largely in the order received.
Other elements of the collection include Volkov's poetry and smaller prose works, some also of an autobiographical nature, as well as evidence reflecting his anti-Communist views and work in America in the 1930s-1950s. The subject file and printed matter series contains brochures and clippings on this and other subjects.
Left unfilmed due to the general accessibility of materials are a large number of boxes containing clippings and printed matter (in Russian and English, from periodicals such as the San Francisco Chronicle and Examiner, Reader's Digest, American Mercury, Look, etc.) relating to diverse subjects, the most significant of which are Communism and anti-Communism in the United States (including large amounts of materials on McCarthy, espionage trials and Communist propaganda and subversion, as well as dossiers on various public figures representing these movements), international affairs (especially the spread of Communism), and domestic affairs in the USSR and its satellites and in the United States. This material covers the period from the 1930s to 1953.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials and copyright to them (with some exceptions) are the property of the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Russia (Territory under White armies, 1918-1920). Armiia.; Ungern-Shternberg, Roman Fedorovich, baron, 1887-1921.; Anti-communist movements--United States.; Communism.; Mongolia--History.; Mongolia.; Russia (Federation); Russian literature.; Russians--United States.; Siberia (Russia)--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union--History--Revolution, 1917-1921.; Soviet Union.; United States--Politics and government.
- Digital File
  Scope and Contents note
  A digital version of Boris Volkov’s “Conscript to Paradise.” This version is important because the physical papers only contain partial and messy drafts, whereas this e-version looks to be prepared for publication. DOC is 461 pages.
- Box 1
  Material not yet described
- Microfilm of the Boris N. Volkov Papers held at the Museum of Russian Culture (Reel 1-23)
  - Microfilm reel conversion list
    Microfilm reel/box conversion list downloadable PDF file
  - Biographical File, 1915-1953. (Box 1)
    General note
    See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/"A Descendant of Genghis Khan" and OVERSIZE FILE/Scrapbooks
    Articles about Volkov, autobiographical notes, correspondence, commercial, employment and service records, arranged alphabetically by physical form
    - Addresses (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Articles about or mentioning Volkov. Includes correspondence with Ripley's Believe It Or Not, regarding Volkov's entry, and correspondence regarding celebrations in honor of Volkov, 1931, 1929 December 19 (Folder 2)
    - Autobiographical notes (Folder 3)
    - Commercial records, Includes materials generated by Volkov as an agent of J.R. Gilchrist & Co.: correspondence with Tientsin Chemical works, K. G. Baturin and Co., Gen. D. L. Khorvat and others, as well as financial documents, 1920-1923. (Folder 4)
    - Correspondence
      - Unidentified family members (?), 1922-1938 and undated (Folder 5)
      - Volkov, Alexander, 1952-1953 (Folder 6)
      - Witte, Boris, 1928 and undated (Folder 7)
    - Description of invention by Volkov - "Etiquette stand" (Folder 8)
    - Employment documents (Folder 9)
    - Identity documents (Folder 10)
    - Inventory of archive (Folder 11)
    - Letter of recommendation for Volkov (Folder 12)
    - Obshchestvo druzei russkoi svobody. See SUBJECT FILE
    - Service records (Folder 13)
    - Subject file - Family
      - Volkov (Townley), Bessie Baldwin (Folder 14)
      - Volkov (Witte), Elena Petrovna (Folder 15)
    - Miscellany (Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1922-1954 (Box 1-2)
    Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
    - General, 1931-1951 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Unidentified, undated and 1948 (Folder 18)
    - Butenko, Vasilii, 1951 (Folder 19)
    - Daniels, Camilla. Includes related correspondence with others. Consists largely of letters and postcards relating to the translation of Volkov's unpublished novel, "Conscript To Paradise." See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS
      - Incoming
        - Undated (Folder 20)
        - 1932-1935 (Folder 21)
        - 1936-1943 (Folder 22)
      - Outgoing, 1933-1943 (and undated) (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Eudin, X. J., 1950 (Folder 2)
    - Izdatel'stvo imeni Chekhova, 1952 (Folder 3)
    - Kaun, Alexander (Folder 4)
    - Konstantinov, P., n.d. (Folder 5)
    - Lubelski, Sergei, 1950 (Folder 6)
    - Lutts, G., 1930 (Folder 7)
    - Mel'gunov, S. (?), 1951 (Folder 8)
    - Novoe Russkoe Slovo, 1951 (Folder 9)
    - Panteleieff, Maxim, 1951 (Folder 10)
    - Postnikova, Taisiia Anatol'evna, 1953 and undated (Folder 11)
    - Rubtsova, T., n.d. (Folder 12)
    - Sakovitch, 1925 (Folder 13)
    - Serebrennikov, I. I., 1929-1930 (Folder 14)
    - Serebrennikova, Aleksandra Nikolaevna, 1929-1933 (Folder 15)
    - Shapiro, Nadia L., 1927-1954 (Folder 16)
    - Shmelev, Ivan S., 1950 (Folder 17)
    - Solonevich, Boris, (fragment). Includes two attached wallet-size photos of Solonevich, n.d. (Folder 18)
    - Tenney, Jack B., Senator, 1948 (Folder 19)
    - Vasil'ev, P., 1931 (Folder 20)
    - Vernadsky, G., 1931 (Folder 21)
    - Miscellany. Consists mostly of fragments of letters (Folder 22)
  - Speeches And Writings, 1913-1950. (Box 2-16)
    See also OVERSIZE FILE
    Articles, drafts of unpublished autobiographical novel, poetry, letters to the editor and reviews, arranged chronologically by title
    - General
      - Fragments (unidentified), Holograph and typescript (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Letters to editor, Holograph and typescript (Folder 24)
      - Poems, Holograph, typescript and printed copies, 1913-1936 and undated. (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
    - "Amerikanskoe pravopisanie," Holograph and typescript (Folder 4)
    - "Armeiskii razskaz," Holograph, n.d. (Folder 5)
    - "Broshiury R. D. O.," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 6)
    - "Chekist li Sergei Gevlich," Typescript, and open letter of S. P. Mel'gunov (Folder 7)
    - "Conscript to Paradise," include unrelated material, n.d. May
      See also Digital File.
      - Background materials. Includes notes by Volkov and others, citations from printed sources, correspondence (between Volkov and various individuals), recollections by others of Mongolia and the activities of Gen. R. F. Ungern-Shternberg in, 1918-1922 (Folder 8-9)
      - Chapter outlines (Folder 10)
      - Contract for the translation of the book (Folder 11)
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1925-1933 (Box 4, Folder 1)
        - Daniels, Camilla. See CORRESPONDENCE
        - Il'ina, Olga, 1927 (Folder 2)
      - Drafts and fragments of drafts. Holograph and typescript. Includes early drafts told from the point of view of E. P. Volkova (Witte)
        - General (Folder 3-7)
        - General (Box 5, Folder 1-5)
        - General (Box 6, Folder 1-8)
        - General (Box 7, Folder 1-10)
        - General (Box 8, Folder 1-5)
      - Drafts and fragments of drafts
        - General (Box 9, Folder 1-3)
        - Primarily English translations (Box 10, Folder 1-7)
        - Primarily English translations (Box 11, Folder 1-9)
        - Primarily English translations (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
      - Final draft (partial) (Folder 4-9)
        - Russian
        - English (Box 13, Folder 1-4)
      - List of photographs, possibly intended for inclusion in book (Folder 5)
      - Prepublication reviews (Folder 6)
      - Synopses and book proposals (Folder 7)
    - "Deti," Holograph, n.d. (Folder 8)
    - "Di Pi staviat khoroshii rekord v SShA," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 9)
    - "Dolina Santa Klary," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 10)
    - "Galantnyia prikliucheniia esaula Malygina," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 11)
    - "Golova voina," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 12)
    - "Goluboe tria-lia-lia," Holograph, n.d. (Folder 13)
    - "Kak pisat'," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 14)
    - "Kamuflet ili nakazannyi samokhval (iz galantnykh prikliuchenii esaula Malygina v SShA)," Typescript, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - ["Khunkhuzy"], Holograph and typescript. Includes background materials and drafts (Folder 2)
    - "Krugosvetnoe puteshestvie mistera Stobsa," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 3)
    - "Kto lgal? (Soedinennye shtaty protiv Aldzher Khissa)," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 4)
    - Letter to the editor, unidentified newspaper, Typescript, n.d. (Folder 5)
    - "Literaturnyi roman ili svoi svoemu ponevole brat," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 6)
    - "Moral'nyia kachestva 'belykh'," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 7)
    - "Ob obychaiakh i obriadakh pri rodakh inorodcheskikh zhenshchin v Sibiri i Srednei Azii," Typescript (fragments), n.d. (Folder 8)
    - "Otboi," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 9)
    - "Our Lady of Chenstohov," Holograph (in Russian), n.d. (Folder 10)
    - "Povest' o shestnadtsatoi neistrebimoi rote," Holograph and typescript (Folder 11)
    - "Protsess Kravchenko s tochki zreniia amerikantsa," Holograph and typescript. Includes background material (clippings) (Folder 12)
    - "Put' poslednikh russkikh kniazei," Typescript. Includes English translation entitled "The Way of the Last Russian Princes", n.d. (Folder 13)
    - "Razgovor po dusham," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 14)
    - Review of Vestnik Kitaia, Typescript, n.d. (Folder 15)
    - Review of Vol'naia Sibir', Typescript, n.d. (Folder 16)
    - "Rubin," Typescript. Includes English translation entitled "The Ruby in the Ring", n.d. (Folder 17)
    - "Second Sight in Tartary," Typescript (Folder 18)
    - "Severo-vostochnyi ugol Pekina," See OVERSIZE FILE, n.d.
    - "Shtab-rotmistr Ianenko-Iankovskii," Holograph and typescript (Folder 19)
    - "Sibirskiia chastushki," Holograph and typescript (Folder 20)
    - "Sila russkago slova," Holograph and typescript (Folder 21)
    - "Sinodik pogibshikh," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 22)
    - "Skazka pro Bielago Bychka," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 23)
    - "Sovnaglost'," Holograph, n.d. (Folder 24)
    - "A Spit," Holograph, n.d. (Folder 25)
    - "Stiv i Pidro - gruzchiki San-Frantsisko," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 26)
    - "Strannyi sluchai gospodina Belfrans," Holograph, n.d. (Folder 27)
    - "Svoboda slova i Amerik. Kommun. Partiia," Holograph and typescript (Folder 28)
    - Translation of "An Open Letter to Frederic Jolio-Curie," signed by ten Nobel Prize Laureates, Typescript, n.d. (Folder 29)
    - Translation of M. Osorgin's "Goluboi kon'," Typescript, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - "Ulybka Vyshinskago," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 2)
    - Untitled article on Cossacks, Typescript, n.d. (Folder 3)
    - Untitled draft of work on U.S. recognition of U.S.S.R., Holograph, n.d. (Folder 4)
    - Untitled draft of review of Western and émigré books and articles on U.S.S.R., Holograph (Folder 5)
    - Untitled memoir of university life, Typescript, n.d. (Folder 6)
    - Untitled summary of notes of A. Jigalin regarding his experiences in China in Holograph, 1945-1947, n.d. (Folder 7)
    - Untitled synopsis of literary work on the Russian Civil War, Holograph, n.d. (Folder 8)
    - Untitled work on Eugene Lyons, Holograph and typescript (Folder 9)
    - Untitled work on experiences during the Russian Civil War, Typescript, n.d. (Folder 10)
    - Untitled work on front-line experiences in Holograph, 1915, n.d. (Folder 11)
    - Untitled work on Russians in San Francisco, Typescript, n.d. (Folder 12)
    - "Vrediteli," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 13)
    - "Vziatie bielymi Troitskosavska i sobytiia na russko-mongol'skoi granitsie g.g.)," n.d. Typescript, (1918-1919 (Folder 14)
    - "Znaiut li chto tvoriat," Typescript, n.d. (Folder 15)
    - "Predel," 1921. See "Predel," and OVERSIZE FILE/Scrapbooks/Clippings I, 1930 July 11
    - "Ob Ungernie," Novosti zhizni, Printed copy, 1921. (Folder 16)
    - "Posliednie dni ungernovshchiny," Zaria, Printed copy, 1921. (Folder 17)
    - "Material ob Ungerne," Typescript. Includes "Ob Ungernie," "Konets Ungerna," "Zagovor protiv Ungerna," and "Ungern v Mongolii", 1921-1931. (Folder 18)
    - "O dnevnike gen. barona A. Budberga," Russkaia zhizn', Background material and printed copy, 1928 February 3. (Folder 19)
    - "Ideal'nyi dom," Russkaia zhizn', Printed copy, 1928 June 3. (Folder 20)
    - "Schast'e rotmistra Gei-Tur," Novaia zaria, Printed copy, 1929 January 9. (Folder 21)
    - "Istinnyia prikliucheniia," n.d. Includes English translation entitled "A Job For a Prince" (notarized and correspondence with Pervaia russkaia kino-studiia, 1924-1931. Typescript, 1929 February 23) (Folder 22)
    - "Meshchanskiia nastroeniia," Novaia zaria, Printed copy, 1929 April 13. (Folder 23)
    - "Sviazyvaiushchee nachalo," Typescript (under the pseudonym of Ivan Zuda), 1929 June 29. (Folder 24)
    - "Predel," Russkaia zhizn', Typescript and printed copy. Possibly related to a 1921 article of the same title, 1930 July 11. (Folder 25)
    - "A Descendant of Genghis Khan," Asia, Printed copy. Includes drafts in English and Russian, entitled "Stepnoi aristocrat." Also includes biographical information, 1931 November. (Folder 26)
    - Untitled profiles of Russian emigrants in the United States, or 1933. Typescript, 1932 (Folder 27)
    - "East and West," Novaia zaria, Typescript of English translation. Includes review of Grace Burrough's dance concert by Flora Reif, 1932 January 23. (Folder 28)
    - V pyli chuzhikh dorog Berlin, [1933]
      - Typescript (Folder 29-30)
      - Proofs (Box 16, Folder 1)
      - Printed copy (Folder 2)
      - Reviews and correspondence (Folder 3)
    - Review of George Stewart, The White Armies, Novaia zaria, Typescript and printed copy. Includes abridged English translation, 1933 August 1. (Folder 4)
    - "Kogda roga prinosili bogatstvo," Novaia zaria, Printed copy, 1933 December 16. (Folder 5)
    - "Amerikanskii korrespondent," Zemlia kolumba, Typescript. Includes abridged English translation, 1936 March. (Folder 6)
    - "Asia's Oldest Democracy," Typescript. Includes Russian and English drafts and related correspondence, 1936. (Folder 7)
    - "Zagadochnaia smert' Krivitskago," Russkaia zhizn', Printed copy, 1949 August 23. (Folder 8)
    - "Komissiia Khuvera," Russkaia zhizn', Printed copy. Includes notes, background materials, and correspondence, 1949 September 17. (Folder 9)
    - "Kak Gor'kii ispol'zoval amerikanskoe mylo," Russkaia mysl', Typescript, 1950 May 12. (Folder 10)
    - Letters to the editor, Russkaia zhizn', Printed copies. Includes background material and correspondence, 1950 August 11 and 30. (Folder 11)
    - "Krestovyi pokhod za svobodu," Typescript. Includes background material, 1950 September 3. (Folder 12)
    - "Son redaktora," Typescript, 1952 September. (Folder 13)
  - Subject File, 1913-1953. (Box 17-20)
    Unless noted otherwise, files consist of clippings and other printed matter
    Mainly clippings, with some correspondence and writings by others, arranged alphabetically by subject
    - Abductions, Political--Europe. Relates to Soviet abductions of anti-Communist figures, particularly in post-World War II Germany, and to the abduction of Gen. A. P. Kutepov in France, 1937 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - American-Russian Institute. Publications and printed matter (Folder 2)
    - Beloff, Georgei. Includes letters to the editor and other correspondence by Volkov and others relating to Beloff's article (also included), "Still Alive," Liberty, 1933 (Folder 3)
    - Bridges, Harry (Folder 4)
    - Catholicism and Eastern Orthodoxy (Folder 5)
    - Cheka (Folder 6)
    - Church of Christ the Savior, Berkeley, CA (Folder 7)
    - Communists, California (Folder 8)
    - Diplomatic and Consular Service, Soviet Union. Relates to the escape of Oksana Kasenkina from the Soviet consulate in New York in and subsequent diplomatic scandal, 1948 (Folder 9)
    - Eastern Orthodox Church. SEE Catholicism
    - Friends of Fighters for Russian Freedom (Folder 10)
    - Grebenshchikov, Georgii (Folder 11)
    - Karelina, Mariia Nikolaevna. Correspondence, including letter, describing her escape from the Soviet Union (Folder 12)
    - Lavrova (Shapiro), Nadia. Typescript and clippings of her articles in various newspapers (Folder 13)
    - Obshchestvo druzei russkoi svobody (Folder 14)
    - Orthodox Eastern Church. Relates to activities of Church in Russia as well as in the United States (Folder 15)
    - Plevitskaia, Nadezhda (Box 18, Folder 1)
    - Press, Russian--Caricatures (Folder 2)
    - Propaganda, Anti-Communist--United States. Includes clippings, correspondence and other printed matter relating to activities of Americans and Russians in this field (Folder 3)
    - Pushkin, Aleksandr Sergeevich. Includes correspondence and newspaper issues for (100th anniversary of Pushkin's death), 1937 (Folder 4)
    - Rasputin, Grigorii (Folder 5)
    - Russian Far East. Brief memoir of life and social customs in Transbaikal region, by unidentified author, 1900-1922 (Folder 6)
    - Russian language (Folder 7)
    - Russians--China
      - General (Folder 8)
      - Shanghai. Includes correspondence and drafts of newspapers articles by various journalists (M. Lidin and others), mainly relating to the post-World War II period (Folder 9)
    - Russians--Foreign countries
      - General (Folder 10)
      - 'Sovpatrioty' (Folder 11)
    - Russkaia zhizn'. Editorials materials and correspondence (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Russkii tsentr (Russian Center), San Francisco
      - General (Folder 2)
      - Clippings (Folder 3-4)
    - Russo-Japanese War, -Causes. Brief (6 p.) holograph on origins of war by unidentified participant, 1904-1905- (Folder 5)
    - San Francisco Workers' Alliance (Folder 6)
    - San Francisco Workers' School (Folder 7)
    - Science, Russian. Includes clippings on Russian and Soviet "firsts": inventions and discoveries (Folder 8)
    - Soviet Union--Emigration and immigration
      - 'Nevozvrashchentsy' (Folder 9)
      - Soviet attitude toward emigrants (Folder 10)
      - 'Vozvrashchentsy' (Folder 11)
    - Tenney, Jack, Senator (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Trebitsch-Lincoln (Folder 2)
    - Zakharoff, Basil (Folder 3)
    - Miscellany. Includes clippings on diverse topics from Russian émigré press in China (Folder 4)
  - Printed Matter, 1932-1953. (Box 20)
    Unsorted brochures on various topics (mainly communism and anti-communism, as well as China and Mongolia), including some rare émigré editions
    - Brochures on various topics, some rare émigré editions (Box 20, Folder 5-10)
  - Photographs, c. 1915-1950. (Box 20)
    Ten photographs include one of Volkov, taken during the First World War, three of Russian translators and interpreters working for the United Nations, and the rest of unidentified people and places